Firstly, it's important to know that not every
policy covers OPD expenses or any
diagnostic tests that may be
required. So, let's say you have
pain in your leg and you have any
pharmacy expenses. For example, let's say the
premium is high because some
plans do have waiting periods, some plans don't have
waiting periods. Hello, everyone, welcome
to another episode of Ask PB by
Policybazaar. Today, we're going to talk
about OPD cover in health insurance. This is
a cover that you
can buy with your health insurance at a very
minimal cost. It covers your regular
doctor visits, medicines, diagnostics, etc.
Joining me today to talk about this is Amit Chhabra, who
is the Chief Business Officer of General Insurance
at Policybazaar. Now, before we dive into our
show today, I just want to highlight a
great initiative by Policybazaar: It's
called FOS and Feet on Street model, wherein
Policybazaar advisors come to your doorstep and consult
you.  We explain about insurance products,
clear all your doubts
so that you can buy insurance from the comfort of your home.
And if you like our
episode today, please don't forget to like,
share and subscribe. Welcome to the show Amit.
Thank you Simran. It's always a pleasure to be here.
So Amit, what expenses are covered in OPD benefit?
So firstly, it is important to know that not every
policy covers OPD expenses. So, if you
want to take a health insurance policy that provides outpatient coverage,
which means if you have to
see a doctor, get any tests done, or buy any medicines, then
first of all, you should
buy a policy that
covers outpatient expenses. They are not covered by default in every policy.
Second, what are the expenses
that are typically covered? So, first is any
consultation charges. For example, if
you go to a doctor, you are going to a general practitioner
or you are going to a specialist,
you are going to a pediatrician.  If
you are going to a gynecologist or anyone else, then
whatever his consultation charges are,
that gets covered as a part of the OPD
benefit. If you have
gone to an orthopedician, I may
request for an X-ray just to know if there is
any damage anywhere. So the
cost of that X-ray is also covered.
Thirdly, apart from this, if there are any pharmacy
expenses, for example, suppose the doctor
prescribes you some painkillers,
any medicine, any muscle relaxant,
prescription
charges, diagnostic tests and pharmacy
expenses, all these three are covered, which is largely what gets and
what you pay when you go to any
outpatient doctor. Now,
Amit, there is a waiting period in health insurance,
right? Is there a waiting period in OPD benefit also? So, it depends
on the plan. Some plans do have waiting periods. Some plans don't have
waiting
periods and they allow coverage from you after that.  While
buying the policy, some plans also
put a waiting period on pre-
existing diseases. So, suppose if you have
diabetes, then there will be a waiting period for diabetes
if there is any
outpatient expense due to diabetes, but everything else will be
covered. So, there may be an initial
waiting period in almost every plan
because otherwise, what happens is that if you are
going to a doctor, then if you
take insurance before going, then that would be wrong,
but apart from that, there is no
waiting period as such, other than if you have a
pre-existing disease, then now OPD
benefit can be claimed multiple
times a year. Yes, absolutely, OPD
expenses are such that you have to
take them again and again in a year, whenever you fall
sick, have viral fever, cold cough,
some injury, that is when you can claim
and it is very very important, their claim
process is quite simple, it is an online process,
so it does not happen that you have to pay for OPD.
Bills have to be collected and couriered to the
insurance company. This used to happen
in the past. Now, a lot of things have become online.
You can go to the mobile app and
upload photos of the bills and the
reimbursement gets credited to your account.
It's a very simple process. You can do it
multiple times in a year. No problem at all. At
Policy Bazaar, we
also help our customers a lot.
In the claim process, you get a relationship
manager. If you want to make a claim on Policy Bazaar, it's
very simple. You just have to
send photos of those bills to your relationship manager. After that, the entire
process, whatever form you have to fill, everything else is taken care of by the
policy relationship manager. Now, with OPD, there is a
cover, an option that you
buy with your health insurance policy. Right,
many people feel that if we
buy something with our health policy,
our premium will increase a lot. Is that true? It
depends on what sum
insured you are taking and what kind of insurance you are taking.  You
want to avail the benefits because there are
many variants in OPD as well. The
premium is high because as a
proportion to the sum insured, the premium is
high. So, suppose if you are
taking a sum insured of Rs. 10,000, then
your premium for Rs. 10,000 is typically Rs. 1500,000. So,
if you look at it in percentage terms,
it is 15 to 20 percent of the sum
insured. Where as an IPD or the
premium that you see for a normal health insurance policy is typically very low
as a percentage. This is because the
chances of claims are higher and
less in IPD. For example, think for yourself
how many times you have gone to see a doctor
outside versus how many times you have been
hospitalized in the last one year or
in the last 5 years. Because the chances of claims are
higher, hence the premium is also a little higher.
But you should see it in such a way that it also has a
high probability.  There is an expense,
specifically I would say if you have
senior citizens or children in your house, then OPD
expenses keep on happening because someone or the other falls
sick, there is some
infection or the other, some problem or the other keeps on happening, so
this is sort of a
guaranteed expense type I would say which always happens, so
OPD insurance helps you in this thing
that it insures that those
expenses do not come in your monthly expenses and the
health insurance covers the expenses,
now Amit the most important
question which I am sure all the viewers would
want to know is how to claim OPD benefit,
yes see as I
said earlier it is a very very simple process it is an
online process it is not an offline
process that you have to courier the bills, it is a
digital process you can go to our app,
on the app you have to just upload the
copy of your bills or if you
want even more simply then you can ask your relationship manager of Policybazaar
for you  Or you can order medicines for
yourself. So the advantage of these cases is
that you don't have to pay anything out of your pocket and everything else
is just automatic, cashless,
taken care of by the insurance company. Amit,
thank you for these wonderful insights. Now
we have some questions from our audience
that have come up during life. Let's look at them. The
first question is
what is included in OPD cover and
how is it different from regular hospitalization coverage. So,
as I said, three
things are covered. First is doctor
consultation, that means if you are going to see a doctor,
his fees, whatever
tests he does for you, etc., his checkup, all those
expenses are covered by your OPD health
insurance policy. Second thing is
if there are any diagnostic tests like
X-ray, MRI, any blood test, the
policy provides it on prescription. Third thing is pharmacy.
For example, suppose the doctor prescribes some medicines,
some syrup,
some ointment, then that is also covered
in your policy.  These three
things are covered. Generally, whenever you visit a doctor,
these three things can happen.
This is where you have to pay.
Your OPD health
insurance policy covers all these things. This is
different from a hospitalization policy
because in a normal health insurance policy,
if you want to make a claim, you have to be
hospitalized. Now, suppose you have
pain in your leg, a fracture, or a
viral infection. If
hospitalization is not required, then
your health insurance
policy does not cover that claim. And you too would
not want to go to the hospital for such a small thing. In
such a situation, this OPD health insurance
policy comes in handy. If I
explain it this way, if we look at all our healthcare
expenses, they are either OPD
or IPD. IPD
is covered by your regular health insurance policy.
Today, most of the people in
India would pay for OPD expenses from their own pocket.
If you also take a good OPD health
insurance policy or as an
add-on to your health insurance
policy, then you can be assured.  That
any healthcare expenditure, whether
outpatient or inpatient, will
not be spent from your pocket and your health
insurance policy will cover it, so your
overall healthcare becomes quite secure.
If you take an OPD policy along with a
health insurance policy, Amit. The
next question is, is there
any capping on visit limit in OPD cover?
Of course, it depends plan to plan. There are
all kinds of plans. Some
plans say that you will
get only Rs. 1000 per visit as consultation
charges. Some plans say that you can
visit as many times as you want, but the
sum insured for your doctor consultation
is only Rs. 1000. Then there are some plans which
say that there are no limits, you can go
as many times as you want. So, that
choice is yours. As a consumer, you must compare
and decide which is the right OPD
health insurance plan to buy. The next question
is, is OPD cover useful for me or does
it increase the premium too much?
See, the premium of OPD health insurance does
not increase much. The
premium that you see upfront remains the same.
Obviously, it will increase a little with age because the chances
of going to a doctor also increase, but
not very much. I would say that in
proportion to the expenses,
this OPD premium is a small number. So, this is why
I always recommend that
you all should also take an OPD health
insurance policy because
if you look specifically, if you live
in tier one cities like Delhi, Bombay, Bangalore, then
the cost of
OPD has gone up significantly.
Earlier, a doctor consultation used to cost Rs 300, 400, 500.
Today, if you see a good doctor for
less than Rs 1000,
you do not even get an appointment. So, the cost of OPD
treatment has gone up significantly. If you
go for any diagnostic test, the
bill for both the treatments is generated in the same way. So, the
cost has gone up.  And given the way things are going,
diseases are increasing so much around us right now, in terms of you know,
having a good diagnostic and going to a good doctor is
very important for your treatment. I don't think
we should ever be stingy in this thing
or we should
think that let me sacrifice my health, which
means it will go wrong for
you. So I always recommend that you should
not compromise with your health
and having a good OPD policy is a very
good option because it insures that you will
never compromise with your own health.
Amit, next question is
can routine health checkup, dental treatment or physiotherapy also be covered in OPD? Of course, see, every type of age, I said, there is
every type of policy, all this
is covered because all this comes under OPD. So,
suppose you have to get physiotherapy done,
you have some problem in your legs or back, for example, if
you have to take physiotherapy sessions, then you get
coverage for that. Any dental treatment of yours gets covered.  There
is a procedure, suppose you have to get a root canal done,
tooth extraction done,
if you are facing any problem, it should not be cosmetic,
but apart from that, if you have any
problem, then all that is also covered, so
if you face any problem in all these types of health care, it gets
covered in your outpatient policy
Amit, thank you so much that you took out time and came to
us and
addressed our queries,
addressed the queries of our audience, thank you so much, thank
you, thank you Simran, always a pleasure and
to our audience, if you guys have any other
questions regarding health insurance,
regarding OPD, regarding the claim process, please leave
a comment and we will take up your questions
in the next episode till then, stay safe